Marriage Equality and LGBT Activism in Connecticut Oral History Collection 2011.0076
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Marriage Equality and LGBT Activism in Connecticut Oral History Collection
2010-2011
2011.0076
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
0.25 Linear feet
The collection consists of 11 oral histories with leading activists in Connecticut who have been a part of the marriage equality movement as well as been engaged in other forms of LGBT activism in the state and beyond. The interviews were conducted by Valerie Love, Curator for Human Rights and Alternative Press Collections, between July 2010 and April 2011. Six of the eleven interviews have been transcribed and are available.
Buckheit, Carol
Glezen, Becky
Glezen, John
Holmes, Susan
King, Fleurette
Love, Valerie
McHaelen, Robin
Pawelek, Josh, Reverend
Reyna, Bessy
Ryker, Karen
Stanback, Anne
Scope and Contents
Transcripts of six of eleven interviews conducted are available online or in hard copy. Interviews conducted by Valerie Love. Transcriptions produced by MediaScribe and edited by Valerie Love.
Project background
The Marriage Equality and Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender (LGBT) Activism in Connecticut Oral History Project was a pilot project of Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries. The collection consists of 11 oral histories with leading activists in Connecticut who have been a part of the marriage equality movement as well as been engaged in other forms of LGBT activism in the state and beyond. The interviews were conducted by Valerie Love, Curator for Human Rights and Alternative Press Collections, between July 2010 and April 2011. Funding for this project was provided by the UConn Libraries Strategic Planning Team, and the Treibick Family Public Outreach Fund in Human Rights. Thanks to Martha McCormick and Heidi Muir of Mediascribe for their transcription work.
History
In 1991, Connecticut became the third state to pass a comprehensive anti-discrimination law concerning sexual orientation in employment, housing, public accommodations and credit. This law barred employers from refusing to hire a person, discharging them, or discriminating against employees because of their sexual orientation. The Connecticut Commission on Human Rights and Opportunities (CHRO) ruled in November 2000 that transgendered people may be protected under the law’s prohibition of sex discrimination.
In October 2000, Connecticut passed a co-parent adoption law, which created a legal process for second parent adoption, regardless of gender. This law allows an existing parent (biological or adoptive) to agree to the adoption of his/her child by another person, including a same gender partner, who shares parental responsibility for the child.
In April 2005, the Connecticut General Assembly passed, “An Act Concerning Civil Unions” (Public Act 05-10), which made Connecticut the second state (after Vermont) to allow civil unions for same-sex couples. Civil unions are a legal status parallel to marriage at the state level, which allow committed same-sex couples to obtain the state level benefits of marriage.
On October 10, 2008, Connecticut joined Massachusetts and California to become the third state to allow same sex-couples to marry. The Connecticut Supreme Court released a ruling in the case, Elizabeth Kerrigan et al v. Commissioner of Public Health et al, overturning the state’s ban on same-sex marriage, stating:
“We conclude that, in light of the history of pernicious discrimination faced by gay men and lesbians, and because the institution of marriage carries with it a status and significance that the newly created classification of civil unions does not embody, the segregation of heterosexual and homosexual couples into separate institutions constitutes a cognizable harm. We also conclude that (1) our state scheme discriminates on the basis of sexual orientation, (2) for the same reasons that classifications predicated on gender are considered quasi-suspect for purposes of the equal protection provisions of the United States constitution, sexual orientation constitutes a quasi-suspect classification for purposes of the equal protection provisions of the state constitution, and, therefore, our statutes discriminating against gay persons are subject to heightened or intermediate judicial scrutiny, and (3) the state has failed to provide sufficient justification for excluding same sex couples from the institution of marriage.”
For more information, Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders (GLAD) has information on LGBT rights in the state of Connecticut.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to lesbian gay bisexual and transgender history. More information on LGBT collections available in the UConn Libraries can be found in the library's Research Guide for LGBT Studies. The records of the organization, Love Makes a Family, are housed in the Manuscripts and Archives Department, Sterling Memorial Library, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut. The finding aid for the collection is available through the Yale University Libraries website. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Provenance and Acquisition
Transcripts resulting from interviews conducted for the project were deposited as an oral history collection in the Archives & Special Collections by the project coordinator in 2011.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Human Rights
- Series I: Interviews, 2010-2011
  - Anne Stanback [31 pages], 2010 (Box 1)
  - Carol Buckheit [31 pages], 2010 (Box 1)
  - Bessy Reyna and Susan Holmes [19 pages], 2010 (Box 1)
  - Reverend Joshua Pawelek [21 pages], 2010 (Box 1)
  - John and Becky Glezen [29 pages], 2010 (Box 1)
  - Karen Ryker [25 pages], 2011
  - Robin McHaelen [17 pages], 2010 (Box 1)
  - David Knapp, 2011
  - Fleurette King [40 pages], 2011 (Box 1)
  - Gannon Long, 2011
  - Shawn Lang, 2011